A Guide to the Markle Foundation records, Record Group 1-Record Group 3 FA024
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Markle Foundation Programs, 1
  - Markle Foundation Programs - Accession 1, 1; 41 Cubic Feet
    - Communications, 1969-1984; 3; 30 Cubic Feet 68 boxes
      - California Council for the Humanities - Martha Glessing and Bruce Sievers, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 79)
        Discretionary grant. Funds for an experimental television series, "Womantime." $15,000, awarded on April 7, 1976.
      - California Council for the Humanities - Martha Glessing and Bruce Sievers, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 80)
      - California Institute of Technology - Telecommunications Policy Research Conference, 1975, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 81)
        Discretionary grant D75032. Support of a conference on policy-relevant research concerning telecommunications to be held at Airlie House, Virginia, Spring '76. $5,000, awarded on June 18, 1975.
      - University of California at Berkeley - Leroy Aarons and Robert C. Maynard, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 82)
        Program grant G77330. Support of an intensive summer training program for minority journalists. $25,000 fy 1978, awarded on June 14, 1977.
        See also Folder 87.
      - University of California at Berkeley - Leroy Aarons and Robert C. Maynard, 1976-1980 (Box 13, Folder 83)
        "Deadline."
      - University of California at Berkeley - Leroy Aarons and Robert C. Maynard, 1976-1980 (Box 13, Folder 84)
      - University of California at Berkeley - Sheldon Renan, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 85)
        Discretionary grant. Regional film centers. For conference on regional development of film centers and services in the U. S. $9,847, awarded on January 11, 1973.
      - University of California at Berkeley - Percy Tannenbaum, 1974-1984 (Box 13, Folder 86)
        Program grant G76002. Communication/information systems for the elderly. To conduct a series of studies on how communications technologies can be used in the delivery of services to the elderly. $275,716 ($113,921 fy 1976, $104,965 fy 1977, $56,930 fy 1978), awarded June 20, 1975.
      - University of California at Berkeley - Charles Ward, 1975-1980 (Box 13, Folder 87)
        Program grant G76010. Support of a summer training program for minority journalists. $25,000 fy 1976, awarded on November 10, 1975.
        See also Folders 82-84.
      - University of California at Berkeley, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 88)
        Discretionary grant D75011. For a study of the cross ownership of the mass media. $2,000, awarded on September 24, 1974.
      - University of California at Irvine - Steven Simmons, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 89)
        Discretionary grant D76017. Support for the preparation of a book, "The Fairness Doctrine & the Media." $11,230, awarded on May 24, 1976.
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School, 1971-1979 (Box 14, Folder 90)
        Program grant. To establish a training and research program in communications law. $144,000, awarded on June 15, 1972. Program grant. Public interest communications law. Further support for a training and research program in communications law. $81,000, awarded on June 11, 1974.
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School - Geoffrey Cowen, 1970-1976 (Box 14, Folder 91)
        Program grant. Public interest communications law. Further support for a training and research program in communications law. $81,000, awarded on June 11, 1974.
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School - Geoffrey Cowen, 1970-1976 (Box 14, Folder 92)
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School - Geoffrey Cowen, 1970-1976 (Box 14, Folder 93)
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School - Tracy Westen, 1976-1980 (Box 14, Folder 94)
        Program grant G.77218. Support continuation of training and research program in communications law. $59,496 ($14,874 fy 1977, $44,622 fy 1978), awarded on March 7, 1977.
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School - Tracy Westen, 1976-1980 (Box 14, Folder 95)
      - University of California at Los Angeles Law School - Tracy Westen, 1976-1980 (Box 14, Folder 96)
      - University of California at San Francisco - Leona Butler, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 97)
        Program grant. Support of a project using commercial television to provide public health education. $350,000, awarded on November 14, 1972.
      - University of California at San Francisco - Leona Butler, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 98)
        Discretionary grant. Health education on commercial television. Support for the Television Health Information Project. $14,000, awarded on November 6, 1973.
      - University of California at San Francisco - Leona Butler, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 99)
      - University of California at San Francisco - Leona Butler, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 100)
      - University of California at San Francisco - Leona Butler, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 101)
      - University of California at San Francisco - Paul Ekman, 1972-1977 (Box 15, Folder 102)
        Discretionary grant. Introduction of television to South Africa. Study of the effects of television programming on the social behavior of South African children. $12,825, awarded on October 16, 1972.
      - University of California at San Francisco - Paul Ekman, 1972-1977 (Box 15, Folder 103)
        Program grant. Effect of television on children in Micronesia. Support for a field study of the effects of television on children. $112,000, awarded on March 12, 1974.
      - University of California at San Francisco - Paul Ekman, 1972-1977 (Box 15, Folder 104)
      - University of California at Santa Cruz - Dean McHenry, 1971-1975 (Box 15, Folder 105)
        Discretionary grant. Cable TV planning. Study to provided the Santa Cruz area with CATV programming. $5,000, awarded on September 12, 1973.
      - Cannes Film Festival - Maurice Bessy, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 106)
        Discretionary grant. American independent films. To pay shipping charges for exhibiting independent American films at Cannes Film Festival. $2,000, awarded on March 18, 1974.
      - Capital News Bureau - Christine Weicher, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 107)
        Discretionary grant D79149. To cover the broadcast costs of the California Gubernatorial Debates sponsored by the League of Women Voters of California. $13,000, awarded on October 24, 1978.
      - Center for Action Research - Eliot Daley and Nicholas Van Dyck, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 108)
        Program grants G77001, G77219. Support of a study to ascertain feasibility of a national endowment for children's television programming and to develop a model for such an endowment. $40,000, awarded on June 25, 1976. Program grant. Support of a feasibility study of a national endowment for children's television programming and to develop a model for such an endowment. $50,000 fy 1977, awarded on March 7, 1977. Discretionary grant D77209. Funds to study feasibility of a national endowment for children's broadcasting. $10,000, awarded on February 11, 1977.
      - Center for Action Research - Eliot Daley and Nicholas Van Dyck, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 109)
      - Center for Action Research - Eliot Daley and Nicholas Van Dyck, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 110)
      - Center for Action Research - Eliot Daley and Nicholas Van Dyck, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 111)
      - Center for Action Research - Eliot Daley and Nicholas Van Dyck, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 112)
      - Center for Public Resources, Inc. - James Henry, 1977-1979 (Box 16, Folder 113)
        Program grant G78101. To study possibilities for broadening programming in commercial radio. $35,000 fy 1978, awarded on November 28, 1977.
      - Center for Public Resources, Inc. - James Henry, 1977-1979 (Box 16, Folder 114)
      - Center for Public Resources, Inc. - James Henry, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 115)
        Program grant G79050. To organize an industry group which will lead the effort to strengthen and diversify commercial radio programming. $151,520 ($51,520 fy 1979, $100,000 fy 1980), awarded on February 5, 1979.
      - Center for Understanding Media - Herman Land, 1972-1976 (Box 17, Folder 116)
        Program grant. To support a study of independent film making. $150,000, awarded on March 15, 1973. Discretionary grant. To complete the study of independent filmmakers. $9,500, awarded on April 3, 1974.
      - University of Chicago - Andrew Greeley, 1970-1975 (Box 17, Folder 117)
        Ethnic journalists.
      - University of Chicago - Andrew Greeley, 1970-1975 (Box 17, Folder 118)
      - University of Chicago - Andrew Greeley, 1970-1975 (Box 17, Folder 119)
      - University of Chicago - Andrew Greeley, 1970-1975 (Box 17, Folder 120)
      - University of Chicago - Paul Hirsch and Horace Newcomb, 1974-1977 (Box 17, Folder 121)
        Program grant G78328. Support of a project to develop new directions for analysis and writing about television by integrating the methods of the social sciences and the humanities. $77,503 ($38,753 fy 1979, $38,750 fy 1980), awarded on June 29, 1978.
      - University of Chicago - Paul Hirsch and Horace Newcomb, 1978-1983 (Box 18, Folder 122)
        Television criticism.
      - University of Chicago - Paul Hirsch and Horace Newcomb, 1978-1983 (Box 18, Folder 123)
      - University of Chicago - Paul Hirsch and Horace Newcomb, 1978-1983 (Box 18, Folder 124)
      - University of Chicago - Eddie Williams, 1969-1974 (Box 18, Folder 125)
        Program grant. Internship program for journalists in urban affairs. $330,000, awarded on June 11, 1970.
      - Children's Television Workshop, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 126)
        General support.
      - Children's Television Workshop, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 127)
        Program grant. Partial support for a planning study for a national television program on health. $37,500, awarded on June 15, 1971.
      - Children's Television Workshop, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 128)
      - Children's Television Workshop, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 129)
      - Children's Television Workshop, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 130)
      - Children's Television Workshop, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 131)
      - Citizen's Communications Center - Nolan Bowie, 1977-1979 (Box 19, Folder 132)
        Program grant G79144. Telecommunications Policy Research Conference. To conduct a conference on research bearing on public policy in the communications field. $15,000 fy 1979, awarded on November 20, 1978.
      - Claremont Graduate School - Darryl Enos, 1970-1980 (Box 19, Folder 133)
        Program grant. Study of Spanish language television audiences. $87,5000, awarded on June 18, 1971. Program grant. Support of a project to increase the effectiveness and use of Spanish-language Only Television as an influence on Mexican immigrants and Chicanos living in the Los Angeles area. $64,777, awarded on November 5, 1973.
      - Claremont Graduate School - Darryl Enos, 1970-1980 (Box 19, Folder 134)
      - Claremont Graduate School - Darryl Enos, 1970-1980 (Box 19, Folder 135)
      - Cleveland State University - Sidney Kraus, 1971-1979 (Box 19, Folder 136)
        Discretionary grant D77002. Support for compiling a volume of studies on the Ford/Carter debates. $4,800, awarded on September 20, 1976. Discretionary grant D77004. For organizing a conference that will review the '76 presidential televised debates. $10,000, awarded on October 29, 1976.
      - Cleveland State University - Sidney Kraus, 1971-1979 (Box 19, Folder 137)
      - Cleveland State University - Sidney Kraus, 1971-1979 (Box 19, Folder 138)
      - Cleveland State University - John Robison, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 139)
        Discretionary grant D76004. America's use of time. For replication of certain questions asked in the 1965 Study of Americans' Use of Time. $2,500, awarded on October 1, 1975.
      - Cleveland State University - John Robinson and Dennis Davis, 1978-1980 (Box 20, Folder 140)
        Program grant G79141. To conduct research on public comprehension of television news. $27,782 fy 1979, awarded on November 20, 1978.
      - Coalition of National Voluntary Organizations/National, 1977-1981 (Box 20, Folder 141)
        Discretionary grant D79371. Council on Philanthropy. Support of a study designed to determine ways the two organizations could better strengthen philanthropy and the overall impact of the non-governmental sector. $10,000, awarded on May 31, 1979.
      - Coalition of National Voluntary Organizations/National, 1977-1981 (Box 20, Folder 142)
      - Columbia University - Marvin Barrett, 1976-1978 (Box 20, Folder 143)
        Survey of broadcast journalism.
      - Columbia University - School of Journalism - W. Phillips Davison, 1972-1976 (Box 20, Folder 144)
        Program grant. For support of a survey and analysis of current trends and future directions in mass communications research. $43,603, awarded on June 15, 1971.
      - Columbia University - School of Journalism - W. Phillips Davison, 1972-1976 (Box 20, Folder 145)
      - Columbia University - School of Journalism - Paul Laskin, 1969-1974 (Box 20, Folder 146)
        Discretionary grant. National television broadcasting policy. Funds to complete book on broadcasting policy. $4,000, awarded on December 3, 1971. Discretionary grant D75014. For completion of Paul Laskin's book on national television broadcasting policy. $400, awarded on November 19, 1974.
      - Columbia University - School of Journalism, 1970-1977 (Box 20, Folder 147)
        Program grant. Support for Columbia Journalism Review. $204,000, awarded on October 28, 1970. Program grant. Further support of the "Columbia Journalism Review." $80,000, awarded on June 15, 1973. Discretionary grant D76011. In support of the Sixth Alfred I. DuPont Columbia University Survey of Broadcast Journalism. $10,600, awarded on March 3, 1976.
      - Columbia University - School of Journalism, 1970-1977 (Box 20, Folder 148)
      - Columbia University - School of Law - Benno Schmidt and Fred Friendly, 1971-1978 (Box 21, Folder 149)
        Program grant. Support of a research and writing program on the relationship of the First Amendment to the electronic media (radio and television). $67,611, awarded on November 14, 1972.
      - Columbia University - Benno Schmidt, 1979-1987 (Box 21, Folder 150)
        Program grant G79364. To research and write a book on the First Amendment and the press. $95,250 ($45,250 fy 1980, $50,000 fy 1981), awarded on June 14, 1979.
      - Committee on Children's Television, 1972-1978 (Box 21, Folder 151)
        Program grant. General Support. $15,000, awarded on November 5, 1973.
      - Committee on Children's Television, 1972-1978 (Box 21, Folder 152)
      - Committee on Children's Television, 1972-1978 (Box 21, Folder 153)
      - Committee on Children's Television, 1972-1978 (Box 21, Folder 154)
      - Committee on Economic Development - Alfred Neal, 1970-1973 (Box 21, Folder 155)
        Program grant. To develop a policy statement on the economic and social impact of the new broadcast media. $25,000, awarded on November 14, 1972. Program grant. Broadcasting and the public interest. To developa policy statement on the economic and social impact of the new broadcast media. $25,000, awarded on November 5, 1973.
      - Committee on Economic Development - Alfred Neal, 1970-1973 (Box 21, Folder 156)
      - Committee on Economic Development - Alfred Neal, 1973-1975 (Box 22, Folder 157)
        Program grant. Broadcasting and the public interest. To developa policy statement on the economic and social impact of the new broadcast media. $25,000, awarded on November 5, 1973.
      - Committee on Economic Development - Alfred Neal, 1973-1975 (Box 22, Folder 158)
      - Committee on Economic Development - Alfred Neal, 1973-1975 (Box 22, Folder 159)
      - Committee on Economic Development - Alfred Neal, 1973-1975 (Box 22, Folder 160)
      - Council on Foundations, 1979-1984 (Box 22, Folder 161)
        D79261, D82221, D82332, D84215, D84108, D85220. General member support. Discretionary grant D79261. For general members support. $4,482, awarded February 21, 1979.
      - Cultural Council Foundation - Cross Creek Center for Work and Environmental Studies - Holographic Film, 1976-1977 (Box 22, Folder 162)
        Discretionary grant D77313. To enlarge and continue and artists-in-residence program in holography. $5,000, awarded on April 18, 1977.
      - Cultural Council Foundation - John Giancola, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 163)
        Program grant G78105. Support of Independent Cinema Artists and Producers under the direction of Katherine Morgan. $19,425 fy 1978, awarded on November 28, 1977.
      - Cultural Council Foundation - John Giancola, 1978-1981 (Box 23, Folder 164)
        Independent cinema artists and producers.
      - Cultural Council Foundation - John Giancola, 1977-1981 (Box 23, Folder 165)
        Program grant G79143. To distribute Independent film and video artists' short subjects to pay television systems (ICAP). $40,000 ($14,000 fy 1979, $20,000 fy 1980, $6,000 fy 1981), awarded on November 20, 1978.
      - Cultural Council Foundation - John Giancola, 1977-1981 (Box 23, Folder 166)
      - Charles R. Drew Medical School - Mitchell Spellman, 1969-1971 (Box 23, Folder 167)
      - Duke University - James Barber, 1975-1978 (Box 23, Folder 168)
        Program grant G77012. Media agenda-making in the 1976 Presidential nominating process. Support of a study to determine how politicians set media strategies for campaigns and how media organizations interact with these campaigns to produce a national media agenda of attention. $30,000 fy 1977, awarded on November 23, 1976.
      - Duke University - Joel Fleischman, 1972-1980 (Box 23, Folder 169)
        Program grant G76013. Support for the establishment of a Center for the Study of Communications Policy at Duke University. $300,000, awarded on June 15, 1973. Program grant. Research study to determine how politicians set media strategies and interact with elite journalists and how elites make decisions. $61,022 fy 1976, awarded on January 9, 1976.
      - Early Learning Center Institute, Inc. - Brook Jones and Margaret Skutch, 1976-1984 (Box 23, Folder 170)
        Program grants G77002, G78108. Participatory television for pre-school children. Support of the creation and evaluation of children's television material which teaches with viewer participation. $85,980 fy 1977, awarded on June 25, 1976. Program grant G78107. Further support of ViceVersaVision's development, testing and promotion of participatory television programming for children in anticipation of broadcast production. $40,400 fy 1978, awarded on November 28, 1977.
      - Early Learning Center Institute, Inc. - Brook Jones and Margaret Skutch, 1976-1984 (Box 23, Folder 171)
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - John Jay Iselin, 1971-1975 (Box 24, Folder 172)
        Program grant. Promotion/advertising for Behind the Lines. $14,000, awarded on November 12, 1971. Program grant. General support for the production of "Behind the Lines", a media review television series. $250,000, awarded on June 15, 1972.
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - John Jay Iselin, 1971-1975 (Box 24, Folder 173)
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - John Jay Iselin, 1973-1976 (Box 24, Folder 174)
        Program grant. Independence campaign. Support of WNET/Channel 13's drive for capital and operating funds. $100,000, awarded on November 22, 1974.
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - John Jay Iselin, 1970-1972 (Box 24, Folder 175)
        "Media Review."
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - John Jay Iselin, 1970-1972 (Box 24, Folder 176)
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - John Jay Iselin, 1972-1975 (Box 24, Folder 177)
        Discretionary grant. "Realidades." Study of public television in the Spanish-speaking community of New York. $15,000, awarded on May 10, 1974.
      - Educational Broadcasting Corporation - Jerrold Zacharias, 1972-1977 (Box 24, Folder 178)
        Teaching math with television.
      - EDUCOM - Henry Chauncey, 1970-1974 (Box 25, Folder 179)
        Program grant. Cable television company. Support for a conference on the potential uses of cable television by universities. $18,000, awarded on November 5, 1973. Discretionary grant. For a conference on cable television and the university. $6,765, awarded on April 6, 1973. Discretionary grant. Research on special interest audiences for television. $5,400, awarded on February 25, 1974. Discretionary grant D75018. To continue efforts to design methods of defining new audiences for public television. $3,053, awarded on November 27, 1974.
      - EDUCOM - Henry Chauncey, 1970-1974 (Box 25, Folder 180)
      - EDUCOM - Henry Chauncey, 1970-1974 (Box 25, Folder 181)
      - EDUCOM - Henry Chauncey, 1970-1974 (Box 25, Folder 182)
      - Emory University - David Cook, 1977-January 1978 (Box 25, Folder 183)
        Program grant G77326. History of American television; support research for a book on the cultural history of video communications. $40,000 fy 1978, awarded on June 14, 1977.
      - Emory University - David Cook, 1977-January 1978 (Box 25, Folder 184)
      - Emory University - David Cook, 1977-January 1978 (Box 25, Folder 185)
      - Emory University - David Cook, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 186)
        History of American television.
      - Emory University - David Cook, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 187)
      - Emory University - David Cook, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 188)
      - Fifth Planning District Commission, 1973-1975 (Box 26, Folder 189)
        Discretionary grant D75009. People Planning program. For expenses of reporting on public's response to "Town Meeting" television program. $2,000, awarded on July 3, 1974.
      - Fifth Planning District Commission, 1973-1975 (Box 26, Folder 190)
      - The Film Forum - Karen Cooper, 1975-1981 (Box 26, Folder 191)
        Independent films.
      - Foreign Policy Association - Sam Hayes, 1967-1974 (Box 26, Folder 192)
        Discretionary grant. "Great Decisions." Support of the potential of CATV stations use of the Great Decisions program. $10,000, awarded on January 25, 1971.
      - The Foundation Center - Thomas Buckman, 1972-1974 (Box 26, Folder 193)
        Discretionary grants D75017, D76007, D77003, D78119, D79258. General support. $2,000, awarded on December 19, 1972. Discretionary grant. General support. $2,000, awarded on December 28, 1973. Discretionary grant D75017. General support. $2,000, awarded on November 26, 1974. Discretionary grant D76007. For general support. $2,000, awarded on December 10, 1976. Discretionary grant D77003. Continued general support. $2,000, awarded on October 22, 1976. Discretionary grant D78119. General support. $2,000, awarded on August 8, 1977. Discretionary grant D79258. General support. $2,000, awarded on December 28, 1978.
      - The Foundation Center - Thomas Buckman, 1975-1987 (Box 27, Folder 194)
      - Foundation for Independent Video - George Stoney, 1975-1976 (Box 27, Folder 195)
        Discretionary grant. Support of a conference entitled "Film and Video, Focus on Change" to be held at MOMA. $3,100, awarded on April 7, 1976.
      - Fund for Investigative Journalism - James Boyd, 1971-1974 (Box 27, Folder 196)
        Program grant D75022. Support for investigative writing. $100,000, awarded on March 16, 1972.
      - Fund for Investigative Journalism - James Boyd, 1971-1974 (Box 27, Folder 197)
      - Fund for Investigative Journalism - James Boyd, 1971-1974 (Box 27, Folder 198)
      - Fund for Investigative Journalism - James Boyd, 1971-1974 (Box 27, Folder 199)